Guide to the Poe Studies Association Records, 1967-2015 RL.01029
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Poe Studies Association records
1967-2015
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Poe Studies Association (U.S.)
RL.01029
6.2 Linear Feet
The Poe Studies Association is a non-profit educational organization of college teachers and other interested persons. It was created to exchange information and ideas relating to Edgar Allen Poe biography and criticism both in the U.S. and abroad. Collection contains such items as the Association by-laws, correspondence, minutes, publications, and an address by Maureen Cobb Mabbott. Correspondence is divided into alphabetical and chronological files whose items discuss the workings of the Association, program arrangements, publications, and research ideas. There are also conference and other administrative files.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Poe Studies Association Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1998, 2008, 2016 and 2019.
Biographical and Historical Note
The Poe Studies Association is a non-profit educational organization of college teachers and other interested persons. It was created to exchange information and ideas relating to Edgar Allen Poe biography and criticism both in the U.S. and abroad. The Association publishes a newsletter and meets in conjunction with Modern Language Association meetings. Honorary members have included Jay B. Hubbell and Richard Wilbur.
Collection Overview
The Poe Studies Association records contain such items as the Association by-laws, correspondence, minutes, publications, and an address by Maureen Cobb Mabbott. Correspondence is divided into alphabetical and chronological files whose items discuss the workings of the Association, program arrangements, publications, and research ideas. There are also conference and other administrative files.
Custodial History
The collection is part of the Jay B. Hubbell Center for American Literary Historiography.
American literature -- Societies, etc. -- History -- 20th century; Scholars -- United States -- Correspondence; American literature -- Study and teaching; American literature -- History and criticism; Literary historians -- United States; Records (documents); Poe Studies Association (U.S.); Poe, Edgar Allan, 1809-1849 -- Criticism and interpretation; Jay B. Hubbell Center for American Literary Historiography; Poe, Edgar Allan, 1809-1849
- Correspondence, 1977-2012 and undated; 1
  - Chronological correspondence, 1977-2004 and undated; 29 folders (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Administrative correspondence concerning a variety of elections, reviews of Poe-related works, reserving hotels for conferences, etc.
  - Chronological Correspondence, 1985-2012; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Chronological correspondence, 1997-2005 (Box 4)
- Alphabetical Files, 1967-1988 and undated; 2
  - Carlson, Eric Walter, 1967-1985; 2 folders (Box 1)
    General correspondence regarding setting up meeting times and enrolling in seminars.
  - Dameron, John Lasley, 1924-1983 (Box 1)
    General correspondence including a letter of recommendation for Dr. John Lasley Dameron to be granted the Distinguished Research award by Memphis State University for his work on Poe.
  - DeFalco, Joseph Michael, 1978-1980 (Box 1)
    Correspondence discussing essays and books regarding Poe.
  - Forclaz, Roger, 1974-1982 (Box 1)
    Correspondence regarding an essay called "Tarr and Fether"
  - Gargano, James W., 1974-1984 (Box 1)
  - Kennedy, John Gerald, 1976-1979 (Box 1)
  - Levine, Stuart George, 1977 (Box 1)
  - McElroy, John Harmon, 1974-1977 (Box 1)
    Correspondence regarding edits and revisions on an essay called "The Black Cat"
  - Ljungquist, Kent Paul, Undated (Box 1)
  - Miller, John C., 1976-1979 (Box 1)
  - Reilly, John Edward, 1972-1983; 2 folders (Box 1)
    Correspondence regarding the formation of the Poe Studies Association. These include letters to the Dickens Society seeking guidance, the initial bylaws of the group, etc.
  - Turner, Arlin, Undated (Box 1)
    Includes a copy of a 1977 newsletter.
  - Stauffer, Donald Barlow, 1976-1984 (Box 1)
  - Black, Lynette C., 1986 (Box 2)
  - Carlson, Eric W., 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - Dameron, J. Lasley, 1984-1986 (Box 2)
  - Fisher, Ben, 1985-1986 (Box 2)
  - Gordian Press, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Hall, G.K., 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - Harrison, George W. M., 1986 (Box 2)
  - Hovey, Ken, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
  - Irwin, John T., 1986 (Box 2)
  - Kaplan, Sidney, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Kennedy, Gerald, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Ketterer, David, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Ljungquist, Ken, 1984-1985 (Box 2)
  - Peter Lang Publishing, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
- Administrative Materials, 1988-2015 and undated; 3
  - Miscellaneous Poe Material, Undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Poe Material, 1986-1987 and undated (Box 2)
  - Conferences, 1988 May 19-21 (Box 1)
  - Conferences, 1999 Oct. 7-10 (Box 1)
    1st International Poe Conference
  - Conferences, 1998-1999; 116 folders (Box 3)
  - Conferences, 2002 Oct. 3-6 (Box 1)
    2nd International Poe Conference
  - First International Conference, 1999 (Box 2)
  - Second International Conference, 2002 (Box 2)
  - Second International Edgar Allan Poe Conference, 2002 (Box 4)
  - Third International Conference, 2009 (Box 2)
  - Third International Edgar Allan Poe Conference, 2009 (Box 4)
  - Fourth International Conference, 2015; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 4th PSA Conference, 2015 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Conference Documents, 1994-2009 (Box 2)
  - Meeting Notes, Undated (Box 1)
  - Meeting Notes, undated (Box 2)
  - Bylaws, Undated (Box 1)
  - Bylaws, undated (Box 2)
  - Member List, Undated (Box 1)
  - Member Lists, 1985-1986 and undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1986 and undated (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Financial Documents, 1986-2002 (Box 2)
  - PSA Publications and Presentations, Undated (Box 1)
  - PSA Flyers, 1996 and undated (Box 2)
  - PSA Newsletter, 1986-1991; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - PSA, 2000-2003 (Box 4)
  - Newsletter Notes and Materials, 1986-1987; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Arthur Gorden Pym Research Conference, 1980-1992 (Box 5)
    - Friday, May 20, 1988 9 AM session (Box 5, Audio-cassette RL.01029-CS-0001)
    - Friday, May 20, 1988 PM--First Session (Box 5, Audio-cassette RL.01029-CS-0002)
    - Friday, May 20, 1988 AM--Second Session (Box 5, Audio-cassette RL.01029-CS-0003)
    - Saturday, May 21, 1988 9 AM Session (Box 5, Audio-cassette RL.01029-CS-0004)
    - Saturday, May 21, 1988 AM Second Session (Box 5, Audio-cassette RL.01029-CS-0005)
    - Saturday, May 21, 1988 G. R. Thompson (Box 5, Audio-cassette RL.01029-CS-0006)
    - Saturday, May 21, 1988 PM Session (Box 5, Audio-cassette RL.01029-CS-0007)
    - Saturday, May 21, 1988 John Barth (Box 5, Audio-cassette RL.01029-CS-0008)